<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ep-patent-document PUBLIC "-//EPO//EP PATENT DOCUMENT 1.7//EN" "ep-patent-document-v1-7.dtd">
<!--This XML data has been generated under the supervision of the European Patent Office -->
<ep-patent-document id="EP12783558B1" file="EP12783558NWB1.xml" lang="en" country="EP" doc-number="2912867" kind="B1" date-publ="20250129" status="n" dtd-version="ep-patent-document-v1-7">
<SDOBI lang="en"><B000><eptags><B001EP>ATBECHDEDKESFRGBGRITLILUNLSEMCPTIESILTLVFIROMKCYALTRBGCZEEHUPLSK..HRIS..MTNORS..SM..................</B001EP><B003EP>*</B003EP><B005EP>J</B005EP><B007EP>0009210-RPUB02</B007EP></eptags></B000><B100><B110>2912867</B110><B120><B121>EUROPEAN PATENT SPECIFICATION</B121></B120><B130>B1</B130><B140><date>20250129</date></B140><B190>EP</B190></B100><B200><B210>12783558.5</B210><B220><date>20121029</date></B220><B240><B241><date>20150529</date></B241><B242><date>20190924</date></B242></B240><B250>en</B250><B251EP>en</B251EP><B260>en</B260></B200><B400><B405><date>20250129</date><bnum>202505</bnum></B405><B430><date>20150902</date><bnum>201536</bnum></B430><B450><date>20250129</date><bnum>202505</bnum></B450><B452EP><date>20240823</date></B452EP></B400><B500><B510EP><classification-ipcr sequence="1"><text>H04W  12/04        20210101AFI20240805BHEP        </text></classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr sequence="2"><text>H04W  36/00        20090101ALI20240805BHEP        </text></classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr sequence="3"><text>H04W  12/041       20210101ALI20240805BHEP        </text></classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr sequence="4"><text>H04W  12/043       20210101ALI20240805BHEP        </text></classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr sequence="5"><text>H04W  36/08        20090101ALI20240805BHEP        </text></classification-ipcr></B510EP><B520EP><classifications-cpc><classification-cpc sequence="1"><text>H04W  12/043       20210101 FI20210101RHEP        </text></classification-cpc><classification-cpc sequence="2"><text>H04W  12/041       20210101 LI20210101RHEP        </text></classification-cpc><classification-cpc sequence="3"><text>H04W  36/08        20130101 LI20240219RHEP        </text></classification-cpc></classifications-cpc></B520EP><B540><B541>de</B541><B542>VERFAHREN, VORRICHTUNGEN UND COMPUTERPROGRAMMPRODUKTE ZUR VERBESSERUNG DER WEITERLEITUNGSSICHERHEIT IN MOBILEN KOMMUNIKATIONSNETZWERKEN</B542><B541>en</B541><B542>METHODS, APPARATUSES AND COMPUTER PROGRAM PRODUCTS ENABLING TO IMPROVE HANDOVER SECURITY IN MOBILE COMMUNICATION NETWORKS</B542><B541>fr</B541><B542>PROCÉDÉS, APPAREILS ET PRODUITS-PROGRAMMES D'ORDINATEUR PERMETTANT D'AMÉLIORER LA SÉCURITÉ DES TRANSFERTS INTERCELLULAIRES DANS DES RÉSEAUX DE COMMUNICATION MOBILE</B542></B540><B560><B561><text>EP-A1- 2 197 147</text></B561><B561><text>GB-A- 2 472 580</text></B561><B561><text>US-A1- 2011 274 276</text></B561><B562><text>"3rd Generation Partnership Project; Technical Specification Group Services and System Aspects; 3GPP System Architecture Evolution (SAE); Security architecture (Release 12)", 3GPP STANDARD; 3GPP TS 33.401, 3RD GENERATION PARTNERSHIP PROJECT (3GPP), MOBILE COMPETENCE CENTRE ; 650, ROUTE DES LUCIOLES ; F-06921 SOPHIA-ANTIPOLIS CEDEX ; FRANCE, vol. SA WG3, no. V12.5.1, 24 October 2012 (2012-10-24), pages 1 - 121, XP050650391</text></B562></B560></B500><B700><B720><B721><snm>HORN, Guenther</snm><adr><str>Prälat-Zistl-Str. 12</str><city>80331 Munich</city><ctry>DE</ctry></adr></B721><B721><snm>EILTS, Hinrich</snm><adr><str>Fischerhauser Weg 113/1</str><city>89079 Ulm</city><ctry>DE</ctry></adr></B721></B720><B730><B731><snm>Nokia Solutions and Networks Oy</snm><iid>101828627</iid><irf>EP100015</irf><adr><str>Karakaari 7</str><city>02610 Espoo</city><ctry>FI</ctry></adr></B731></B730><B740><B741><snm>TBK</snm><iid>100061560</iid><adr><str>Bavariaring 4-6</str><city>80336 München</city><ctry>DE</ctry></adr></B741></B740></B700><B800><B840><ctry>AL</ctry><ctry>AT</ctry><ctry>BE</ctry><ctry>BG</ctry><ctry>CH</ctry><ctry>CY</ctry><ctry>CZ</ctry><ctry>DE</ctry><ctry>DK</ctry><ctry>EE</ctry><ctry>ES</ctry><ctry>FI</ctry><ctry>FR</ctry><ctry>GB</ctry><ctry>GR</ctry><ctry>HR</ctry><ctry>HU</ctry><ctry>IE</ctry><ctry>IS</ctry><ctry>IT</ctry><ctry>LI</ctry><ctry>LT</ctry><ctry>LU</ctry><ctry>LV</ctry><ctry>MC</ctry><ctry>MK</ctry><ctry>MT</ctry><ctry>NL</ctry><ctry>NO</ctry><ctry>PL</ctry><ctry>PT</ctry><ctry>RO</ctry><ctry>RS</ctry><ctry>SE</ctry><ctry>SI</ctry><ctry>SK</ctry><ctry>SM</ctry><ctry>TR</ctry></B840><B860><B861><dnum><anum>EP2012071350</anum></dnum><date>20121029</date></B861><B862>en</B862></B860><B870><B871><dnum><pnum>WO2014067542</pnum></dnum><date>20140508</date><bnum>201419</bnum></B871></B870></B800></SDOBI>
<description id="desc" lang="en"><!-- EPO <DP n="1"> -->
<heading id="h0001"><b><u>Field of the invention</u></b></heading>
<p id="p0001" num="0001">The present invention relates to methods, apparatuses and computer program products enabling to improve handover security in mobile communication networks. In particular, the proposed methods, computer program products and apparatuses are for example applicable to scenarios within such networks, e.g. within an evolved packet system EPS network, in order to improve security of handovers HO taking place on a particular interface within such system.</p>
<heading id="h0002"><b><u>Background</u></b></heading>
<p id="p0002" num="0002">Mobile data transmission and data services are constantly making progress. With the increasing usage of mobile communication, network organization and optimization is becoming more and more important. Also, in such context, security of handovers is being investigated, e.g. in the framework of LTE<sup>™</sup> or LTE<sup>™</sup>-A and e.g. the EPS system and interfaces thereof, such as the so-called S1 interface between a network mobility entity e.g. also known as a mobility management entity, MME, and an access node providing (wireless) network access to a terminal such as a user equipment UE, the access node being e.g. also known as evolved NodeB, eNB.</p>
<p id="p0003" num="0003">Insofar, the present invention relates in particular but without limitation to mobile communications, for example to environments under LTE<sup>™</sup> (Long Term Evolution) or LTE<sup>™</sup>-A (LTE<sup>™</sup> Advanced), or any other communication scenario, potentially standardized by 3GPP (3<sup>rd</sup> Generation Partnership Project), ETSI (European<!-- EPO <DP n="2"> --> Telecommunication Standards Institute) and/or other local or regional standardization bodies e.g. NGMN (Next Generation Mobile Networks), and can advantageously be implemented as or in chipsets, or modules, or units, or apparatuses of devices (e.g. network entities such as a transceiver device also known as base station, or NodeB, or evolved NodeB eNB, or e.g. a mobility management entity MME) forming part of those networks, as well as related terminal devices such as a so-called user equipment UE (e.g. smart-phones, a network-access enabled computers or laptops, or the like).</p>
<p id="p0004" num="0004">More particularly, as a specific example referred to in order to describe aspects of the present invention, the present invention relates to those apparatuses / units of devices or network entities that are applied in such communication networks or a part thereof, e.g. known as evolved packet system, EPS, network. Thus, security of handovers HO in such EPS network and security of handovers taking place with involvement of particular interfaces in such system, such as the so-called S1 interface between a MME and a eNB, are being considered.</p>
<p id="p0005" num="0005">With the evolution of LTE<sup>™</sup> and/or EPS system, such cellular networks will become more and more complex, various and huge. For network operators, along with the uses of new technologies, to maintain security and/or data integrity is a big challenge.</p>
<p id="p0006" num="0006">The present invention relates to the security of handovers in LTE, and more specifically to failures of so-called S1 handovers, i.e. handovers, in which not only the eNBs, but also the MME are involved. Security of handovers is for example specified in 3GPP TS 33.401, more specifically in clause 7.2.8. thereof.</p>
<p id="p0007" num="0007"><figref idref="f0001">Fig. 1</figref> illustrates some typical scenario for explanatory purposes. A network mobility entity referred to as mobility management entity MME is denoted by numeral 1. The MME has an interface /connection to other entities of the EPS (not shown in <figref idref="f0001">Fig.1</figref>). Further, the MME has an interface known as S1 interface (S1-I/F) towards each of a plurality of access nodes referred to as evolved NodeBs, eNBs. Such access node eNB provides network access based on e.g. a wireless access technology for one or more terminals referred to as user equipments UE and denoted by numeral 4 and 4', respectively. A source eNB denoted by numeral 2 is labeled as eNB #A. A target eNB denoted by numeral 3 is labeled as eNB #B. The expression source and target pertains to an assumed mobility of a<!-- EPO <DP n="3"> --> terminal UE (4, 4'). Namely, with a moving UE, a UE is at a time t1 served by eNB #A, but after a handover HO served by a eNB #B. An interface between eNBs is referred to a X2 interface, X2 I/F. An interface between an eNB, 2 and 3, respectively, and a terminal UE, 4 or 4', is referred to as Uu interface. In case of a handover between eNBs having an interface X2 there between, the HO typically takes place via the X2 interface. In case of a HO between eNBs without an X2 interface there between, the HO involves the S1 interface. In case of a HO via S1 interface, the MME derives, inter alia, parameters and/or keys such as {NH, NCC} and informs at least the NCC thereof to the target eNB which forwards it to the UE handed over in a handover command that is sent from the target eNB to the UE via the source eNB. Thus, NCC is forwarded to UE in a handover command that is sent from the target eNB to the UE via the source eNB, i.e. target eNB does not directly send NCC to UE over Uu.</p>
<p id="p0008" num="0008">In order to establish security in such EPS system architecture, various keys are established and/or derived in a hierarchical manner. E.g. a key K as a master or base key is stored permanently in an authentication centre AuC and universal subscriber identity module USIM. Using that key and various procedures such as one known as AKA (Authentication and Key Agreement) plural other keys in the hierarchical EPS system are generated and/or derived. Keys used at a specific entity or at a level of similar entities are also referred to herein as local level keys, whereas keys used to derive those may be referred to as higher level keys (determined/kept at hierarchically higher entities or nodes).</p>
<p id="p0009" num="0009">A key K_eNB, for example, is a eNB base key and set up / derived as intermediate key in a MME and UE based on other keys, e.g. upon a state transition of a terminal and/or by the UE and a target eNB upon handover of the terminal.</p>
<p id="p0010" num="0010">Particular focus in relation to the present invention will have to be put on keys referred to as "next hop", NH, and "next hop chaining counter", NCC, as will be explained below.</p>
<p id="p0011" num="0011">The use of Next Hop Chaining Counter (NCC) and Next Hop parameter (NH) is specified in TS 33.401, clause 7.2.8. Both the UE and the MME can derive NH from the current K_ASME, which was formerly generated and kept by MME and UE, and K_eNB in an iterative fashion according to TS 33.401, Annex A.4, when they know the K_ASME, K_eNB and the number of iterations, cf. TS 33.401, clause 7.2.2.<!-- EPO <DP n="4"> --></p>
<p id="p0012" num="0012">The NCC consists of the three least significant bits of the number of iterations performed in computing NH. Only NCC is transmitted to the UE in a handover for efficiency reasons. The UE can correctly derive a new NH from the currently stored {NH, NCC} pair and a newly received NCC only if that newly received NCC relates to an NH that was computed in the MME by at most seven iterations from the NH equal to the one stored in the UE. (This is a simple consequence of the fact that NCC has only three bits.)</p>
<p id="p0013" num="0013">In an S1 handover, the MME computes a new NH parameter, thereby increasing NCC by 1 - with the exception marked with (**) below - and sends the {NH, NCC} pair to the target eNB. After a successful S1 handover, both UE and MME will have the same {NH, NCC} pair stored. When the S1 handover fails the MME will have increased NCC by 1 while the NCC in the UE will remain the same.</p>
<p id="p0014" num="0014">(**) Exception: The first NH sent to an eNB after the K_eNB was established corresponds to NCC=2, according to the rules in TS 33.401, clause 7.2.8.</p>
<p id="p0015" num="0015">In an X2 handover (including the Path Switch procedure), the MME computes a new NH parameter, thereby increasing NCC by 1 - but see exception (**) above - , and sends the {NH, NCC} pair to the target eNB, in the Path Switch Acknowledge message, i.e. only after the handover had been successfully completed between UE, source eNB and target eNB.</p>
<p id="p0016" num="0016">So, an unsuccessful X2 handover has no effect on the NCC value in UE and MME. The new {NH, NCC} pair created in a successful X2 handover will be used only in the next vertical X2 handover, hence the UE will not learn about this new NCC value until then. While the effect of a successful X2 handover (including the Path Switch procedure) on the NCC value in the MME is straightforward the effect on the NCC value in the UE is a bit tricky to determine and depends on the history of handovers as follows:<br/>
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"> -->If the current X2 handover is the first successful (S1 or X2) handover after the K_eNB was established then NCC does not change in the UE; the difference between the NCC values in UE and MME after the current X2 handover increases by 1 (if there was a preceding failed S1 HO) or 2 otherwise, cf. (**) above ).</p>
<p id="p0017" num="0017">If the preceding successful handover was an S1 handover then NCC does not change in the UE; the difference between the NCC values in UE and MME after the current X2 handover increases by 1;<br/>
If the preceding successful handover was an X2 handover then NCC in the UE is set to the value of the NCC sent by the MME in that preceding handover; the amount by which the NCC value increases in the UE depends on the history even before that preceding handover; but the difference between the NCC values in UE and MME after the current X2 handover is more amenable to computation: it is equal to the number of failed S1 handovers between the current and the preceding X2 handovers plus 1.</p>
<p id="p0018" num="0018">It was observed in laboratory tests by applicant that S1 handover failures may lead to loss of synchronization of so-called NextHop (NH) parameter between UE and MME and consequently to a connection failure. Namely, applicant observed in laboratory tests that S1 handover requests could be rejected several times, while the UE remained connected to the same source eNB. Those tests involved a low mobility case, in a scenario where a laptop was being moved from one corner of a building to another one. This move caused an S1 handover attempt, which failed due to the target eNB being congested. By this, the NCC value was increased by 1 in the MME while it remained the same in the UE, because the new NCC value could not propagate from the MME via the new target eNB towards the UE due to the handover failure, or, stated in other words, because the new NCC will only be propagated to UE if the handover actually happens.</p>
<p id="p0019" num="0019">The radio conditions permitted the UE to remain connected to the source eNB. As the laptop did not move any further the radio conditions did not change any further, and, after some time, another S1 handover attempt was made, failing again (and increasing the NCC value in the MME again), while the UE still remained connected to the source eNB. When finally a successful (S1 or X2) handover was made this then led to a condition<!-- EPO <DP n="6"> --> (according to the 'background' information above) where a UE and an MME would compute different NH parameters and, hence, the UE and the eNB would compute different AS level cryptographic keys, leading to a connection failure.</p>
<p id="p0020" num="0020">The observed scenario is plausible enough, and the negative impact sufficiently important, to warrant implementing countermeasures.</p>
<p id="p0021" num="0021">Generally, prior art can be found in 3GPP TS 33.401 and the related stage 3 specifications 3GPP TS 24.301 and 3GPP TS 36.331. An NCC length of three bits has so far been considered sufficient to prevent any loss of synchronization due to handover failures.</p>
<p id="p0022" num="0022">To the inventors' knowledge, the failure case observed in applicant's laboratory tests described above has not been publicly discussed yet. Hence, as the problem had not been revealed, no countermeasures have been proposed so far.</p>
<p id="p0023" num="0023">Generally, as a countermeasure it is conceivable to use a K_eNB re-keying as specified in 3GPP TS 33.401, clause 7.2.9.2. This could be used to resynchronize the NH parameter in MME and UE. The big disadvantage of this re-keying procedure is that it requires a run of the EPS AKA authentication protocol. This, however, is undesirable as operators are currently looking for ways to reduce the load on the home subscriber server, HSS, caused by authentications, which is considered too high already.</p>
<p id="p0024" num="0024">Thus, there is still a need to further improve such systems.</p>
<p id="p0025" num="0025">Prior art is disclosed in document <nplcit id="ncit0001" npl-type="s"><text>3GPP Standard; 3GPP TS 33.401, vol. SA WG3, no. V12.5.1, 24 October 2012</text></nplcit>, describing digital cellular telecommunications system (Phase 2+); Universal Mobile Telecommunications System (UMTS); LTE; 3GPP System Architecture Evolution (SAE); and Security architecture. Further prior art is disclosed in<!-- EPO <DP n="7"> --> <patcit id="pcit0001" dnum="EP2197147A1"><text>EP 2 197 147 A1</text></patcit>, describing a method and apparatus for updating a key in an active state, as well as in document <patcit id="pcit0002" dnum="GB2472580A"><text>GB 2 472 580 A</text></patcit>, describing telecommunications network security.</p>
<heading id="h0003"><b><u>Summary</u></b></heading>
<p id="p0026" num="0026">Various aspects of examples of the invention are set out in the claims.</p>
<p id="p0027" num="0027">According to aspects of the present invention, there are provided an apparatus as set out in claim 1 and a method as set out in claim 9.</p>
<p id="p0028" num="0028">Advantageous further developments are as set out in respective dependent claims in relation to each of the above aspects.</p>
<p id="p0029" num="0029">According to a further aspect of the present invention, there are provided computer program products, as set out in claim 15, comprising computer-executable components which, when the program is run on a computer, are configured to implement and/or carry out the above method aspects. Those computer program product/products may be embodied as a computer-readable storage medium.</p>
<p id="p0030" num="0030">Thus, improvement is based on methods, apparatuses and computer program products according to at least one or more embodiments covered by the above aspects.</p>
<p id="p0031" num="0031">For example:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="dash" compact="compact">
<li>the concepts as presented in line with aspects of the invention are in particular applicable for an eNodeB and/or a MME, for example;<!-- EPO <DP n="8"> --></li>
<li>more particularly, the concepts as presented in line with aspects of the invention will also be applicable to e.g. a follow-up version of 3GPP TS 33.401, "Security of handovers" as e.g. specified in particular in its clause 7.2.8., and lead to an updated version thereof;</li>
<li>aspects of the invention encompass countermeasures which prevent that {NH, NCC} pairs in UE and MME get out of synch due to a number of S1 handover failures;<!-- EPO <DP n="9"> --></li>
<li>one aspect suppresses a key change performed by a terminal,</li>
<li>another aspect prevents a AKA run being necessary to be performed.</li>
</ul></p>
<heading id="h0004"><b><u>Brief description of drawings</u></b></heading>
<p id="p0032" num="0032">For a more complete understanding of example embodiments of the present invention, reference is now made to the following descriptions taken in connection with the accompanying drawings in which:
<ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
<li><figref idref="f0001">Figure 1</figref> illustrates an overview of some entities of an EPS network and interfaces there between;</li>
<li><figref idref="f0002">Figure 2</figref> illustrates a schematic signaling diagram according to an aspect or embodiment of the invention;</li>
<li><figref idref="f0003">Figure 3</figref> illustrates a schematic signaling diagram according to a further aspect or embodiment of the invention</li>
<li><figref idref="f0004">Figure 4</figref> illustrates an example of a basic block circuit diagram of a network mobility entity, e.g. a MME, or an access node, such as a eNB.</li>
</ul></p>
<heading id="h0005"><b><u>Description of exemplary embodiments</u></b></heading>
<p id="p0033" num="0033">Examples of aspects of the invention will be described herein below.</p>
<p id="p0034" num="0034">In various standards, different names may apply for those entities. Therefore, as a mere example only that was chosen to describe a possible implementation framework of the<!-- EPO <DP n="10"> --> present invention, reference is made to LTE<sup>™</sup> EPS and related documents, especially 3GPP TS 33.401. Abbreviations and definitions as set out in such documents/context shall also apply for the purpose of describing at least concepts / embodiments of this invention, though those are not intended to limit the applicability of those concepts / embodiments to other telecommunication environments.</p>
<p id="p0035" num="0035">In brief, according to at least aspects of the invention, countermeasures are proposed which prevent that {NH, NCC} pairs of keys in a terminal UE and MME get out of synchronization due to a number of S1 handover failures.</p>
<p id="p0036" num="0036">Generally, in terms of a network mobility entity, e.g. a MME, aspects of the invention encompass an apparatus, comprising a memory unit; and a control unit connected to the memory unit, the apparatus being configured to interface at least one access node wherein the control unit of the network mobility entity is configured to process one or more higher level security keys received from a network entity to derive at least one local level security key within an established security context for a terminal, forward said derived local security key to at least one access node, detect failures in a handover for a terminal being served by a first access node towards a second access node, wherein the failures in the handover concern the interface between the apparatus and said second access node, verify a trigger condition based on the handover failure history, and responsive to the trigger condition verified, invoke a context modification procedure to re-adjust local level security keys with keys maintained at the terminal within the established security context.</p>
<p id="p0037" num="0037">The at least one local level security key is a next hop, NH, key and a next hop chaining counter, NCC. Further, the trigger condition represents a number of past failed handovers concerning the interface between the apparatus and said second access node. The number of past failed handovers is used to limit the maximum difference of next hop chaining counter, NCC, in the MME and the UE. I.e. with NCC being 3 bit only a maximum number/count of 7 is possible before NCC wraps around, so that with due account of the above description in the background section, the trigger condition will be 5 failed S1 handovers. With this trigger condition, it can be avoided that the difference in the NCC values in the MME and the UE increases beyond 7 if the trigger condition triggers an action that leads to a re-synchronization of NCC in MME and UE. However, in case of a<!-- EPO <DP n="11"> --> NCC being less or more than 3 bit in length, the number of failed S1 handovers as trigger condition will vary accordingly (e.g. in case of a NCC of 4 bit and maximum count of 15 being possible, the trigger condition would be 13 failed S1 handovers).</p>
<p id="p0038" num="0038">In relation to the MME, a particular aspect involves that the context modification procedure invoked is a terminal context modification procedure associated to the terminal to be handed over. Hence, here the control unit is configured to compose a terminal context modification request message comprising the latest local security keys, wherein next hop chaining counter, NCC, as one of the local level security keys is included in a distinct information element, and forward it to the first access node.</p>
<p id="p0039" num="0039">In relation to the MME, another particular aspect involves that the context modification procedure invoked is a network access stratum security mode procedure associated to the terminal to be handed over. Hence, here the control unit is further configured to initiate a new network access stratum security mode procedure based on an evolved key set identifier, eKSI, and associated algorithms, obtain, as a result thereof, an updated parameter for such procedure, process the obtained updated parameter together with an intermediate base key of an access security management entity, K_ASME, to derive therefrom a fresh access node base key, K_eNB, as a local level security key, and forward it to the access node that is currently serving the terminal.</p>
<p id="p0040" num="0040">With reference to aspects related to an access node, eNB, aspects involve an apparatus, comprising a memory unit; and a control unit connected to the memory unit, the apparatus being configured to interface at least a network mobility entity, wherein the control unit is configured to receive a message from the network mobility entity invoking a context procedure to re-adjust local level security keys with keys maintained at the terminal within the established security context.</p>
<p id="p0041" num="0041">A particular aspect of the eNB involves that the control unit is further configured to receive a terminal context modification request message comprising the latest local security keys, detect that a next hop chaining counter, NCC, as one of the local level security keys is included in a distinct information element, responsive thereto invalidate a key change<!-- EPO <DP n="12"> --> indicator, and compose an access resource connection reconfiguration message including the invalidated key change indicator for transmission towards the terminal.</p>
<p id="p0042" num="0042">Another particular aspect thereof involves that the control unit of the access node is further configured to receive, resulting from a network access stratum security mode procedure invocation associated to the terminal to be handed over, a fresh access node base key, K_eNB, as a local level security key from the network mobility entity, and perform re-keying of temporary keys using that fresh key, to derive, based thereon, at least one local level security key.</p>
<p id="p0043" num="0043">Similar notions as made above with reference to apparatus aspects apply likewise to related method aspects.</p>
<p id="p0044" num="0044">The above will be set out in greater detail with reference to the signaling diagrams in <figref idref="f0002">Figs. 2</figref> and <figref idref="f0003">3</figref>. In both Figures, entities (potentially) involved are depicted in horizontal direction and are as those explained with reference to <figref idref="f0001">Fig. 1</figref>. A processing at the respective entity is depicted in vertical direction, thus at least partly also reflecting the series of processing in time. Signaling exchanged is illustrated by arrows from one entity to another entity.</p>
<p id="p0045" num="0045">According to one aspect of the invention, as illustrated in <figref idref="f0002">Fig. 2</figref>, there is proposed a solution which enforces an {NH, NCC} alignment by a modified S1AP: UE CONTEXT MODIFICATION procedure.</p>
<p id="p0046" num="0046">As shown in <figref idref="f0002">Fig. 2</figref>, a MME 1 detects in a stage S20 a trigger condition. In a subsequent stage S21, the MME (a control unit of an apparatus thereof) composes a UE context modification message including the NCC in an information element thereof. In a stage S22, the MME sends this message to the source eNB.<!-- EPO <DP n="13"> --></p>
<p id="p0047" num="0047">The eNB #A (numeral 2), in a stage S23, detects the information element IE including the NCC in the message received. Responsive thereto, in stage S24, it invalidates a key change indicator that would otherwise be set. In a stage S25, the eNB #A composes a RRC connection reconfiguration message including the invalidated key change indicator, and sends it in a stage S26 to the terminal UE (4, 4') i.e. the invalidated key change indicator means that this parameter is not set in the message. The UE then proceeds "as normal" based on this message with the changed (not set) parameter which in the end will serve to align the {NH, NCC} keys.</p>
<p id="p0048" num="0048">Thus, as described above, in brief, if a selected trigger condition (cf. below for an example) is fulfilled the MME sends S1AP: UE CONTEXT MODIFICATION to eNB to enforce {NH, NCC} alignment via intra-cell handover. The MME sends its latest {NH, NCC} pair to the eNB, which applies it using intra-cell handover. This solution requires an extension of the S1AP: UE CONTEXT MODIFICATION procedure by including a new IE for the NCC. Furthermore, when receiving such a modified S1AP: UE CONTEXT MODIFICATION message with the NCC included, the eNB would have to send the corresponding RRCConnectionReconfiguration message with the keyChangelndicator IE not set, contrary to how the eNB currently reacts.</p>
<p id="p0049" num="0049">According to another aspect of the invention, as illustrated in <figref idref="f0003">Fig. 3</figref>, there is proposed a solution which introduces a new K_eNB re-keying procedure without AKA.</p>
<p id="p0050" num="0050">As shown in <figref idref="f0003">Fig. 3</figref>, a MME 1 detects in a stage S30 a trigger condition. In a subsequent stage S31, the MME (a control unit of an apparatus thereof) initiates a network access stratum NAS SMC procedure. This procedure uses the eKSI &amp; NAS algorithm of the current EPS NAS security context. As a result thereof, in stage S32 an updated parameter of the latest NAS SMC message is obtained i.e. the parameter 'uplink NAS COUNT used in the latest NAS Security Mode Complete message'. Based on that updated parameter a new K_eNB is computed based on the existing/known K_ASME in a stage S33, and then sent to the eNB #A (denoted by numeral 2) currently serving the UE in stage S34. The eNB 2 in a stage S35 detects the new K_eNB and subsequently in stage S36 performs re-keying of K_eNB* based on the (temporary) new K_eNB by sending a RRC connection reconfiguration message including the key change indicator set, i.e. valid. This establishes<!-- EPO <DP n="14"> --> a new K_eNB, which leads to NH and NCC being reset in the MME and the UE, i.e. NH is set equal to K_eNB and NCC is set to zero. This achieves the desired re-adjustment of NH and NCC in MME and UE. Namely, when a new K_eNB is established, as is the case here, this amounts to a reset for NH and NCC, i.e. NH is now equal to K_eNB and NCC=0 in both MME and UE. Therefore, the desired re-synchronisation of NH and NCC in MME and UE is achieved at this point.</p>
<p id="p0051" num="0051">Subsequently, (not shown in <figref idref="f0003">Fig. 3</figref>), the flow process could continue for example in that after S36, a message, e.g. a RRC connection reconfiguration message including the key change indicator set mentioned above, is sent from eNB to UE instructing to change K_eNB. Thereupon, as a processing action inside the UE, the UE performs a reset of {NH, NCC}, acknowledges this in a message from the UE to eNB indicating successful reset, which is propagated further from the eNB to the MME indicating success. Thereupon, also a processing action inside the MME performs a reset of {NH, NCC}.</p>
<p id="p0052" num="0052">Thus, as described above, in brief, if a selected trigger condition (cf. below for an example) is fulfilled the MME invokes a new K_eNB re-keying procedure. This procedure is based on the idea that a fresh K_eNB can be derived also from an existing K_ASME if only the parameter 'uplink NAS COUNT used in the latest NAS Security Mode Complete message' is updated before the K_eNB derivation by running a new NAS Security Mode procedure with the same eKSI and algorithms as the current EPS NAS security context. This solution avoids the undesirable additional run of an EPS AKA authentication.</p>
<p id="p0053" num="0053">An example of a trigger condition mentioned for <figref idref="f0002">Figures 2</figref> and <figref idref="f0003">3</figref> is as follows: The number of failed S1 HOs after initial K_eNB establishment is counted, and when this counter reaches the value 5 then the establishment of a new K_eNB is triggered.</p>
<p id="p0054" num="0054">Although at least aspects of the invention have been explained herein above with a rather general reference to impacts on existing standards, with regard to above other aspect, this would particularly effect sections 7.2.8.4 and 7.2.9.2 of 3GPP TS 33.401 as outlined e.g. herein below as embraced by the intermediate asterisks lines:<br/>
*****************</p>
<heading id="h0006"><b><i>7.2.8.4.3 S1-Handover</i></b></heading><!-- EPO <DP n="15"> -->
<p id="p0055" num="0055">Upon reception of the HANDOVER REQUIRED message the source MME shall increase its locally kept NCC value by one and compute a fresh NH from its stored data using the function defined in Annex A.4. The source MME shall store that fresh pair and send it to the target MME in the S10 FORWARD RELOCATION REQUEST message. The S10 FORWARD RELOCATION REQUEST message shall in addition contain the K_ASME that is currently used to compute {NH, NCC} pairs and its corresponding eKSI.</p>
<p id="p0056" num="0056">The target MME shall store locally the {NH, NCC} pair received from the source MME. The target MME shall then send the received {NH, NCC} pair to the target eNB within the S1 HANDOVER REQUEST.</p>
<p id="p0057" num="0057">Upon receipt of the S1 HANDOVER REQUEST from the target MME, the target eNB shall compute the K_eNB to be used with the UE by performing the key derivation defined in Annex A.5 with the fresh{NH, NCC} pair in the S1 HANDOVER REQUEST and the target PCI and its frequency EARFCN-DL. The target eNB shall associate the NCC value received from MME with the K_eNB. The target eNB shall include the NCC value from the received {NH, NCC} pair into the HO Command to the UE and remove any existing unused stored {NH, NCC} pairs.</p>
<p id="p0058" num="0058">NOTE: The source MME may be the same as the target MME in the description in this subclause. If so the single MME performs the roles of both the source and target MME, i.e. the MME calculates and stores the fresh {NH, NCC} pair and sends this to the target eNB.</p>
<p id="p0059" num="0059">For S1-handover, the source eNB shall include AS algorithms used in the source cell (ciphering and integrity algorithms) in the source to target transparent container that shall be sent to the target eNB. The AS algorithms used by in the source cell are provided to the target eNB so that it can decipher and integrity verify the RRCReestablishmentComplete message on SRB1 in the potential RRCConnectionRe-establishment procedure.</p>
<p id="p0060" num="0060">Failed S1 handovers cause the NCC value to increase in the MME while it remains the same in the UE. Repeated failed S1 handovers may hence cause loss of synchronisation of {NH, NCC} pairs in the UE and MME and cause connection failures. The MME shall implement suitable trigger condition(s) and shall invoke a K_eNB re-keying procedure, as described in clause 7.2.9.2, when one of these trigger conditions is met in order to prevent synchronisation loss of {NH, NCC} pairs. When a non-current partial or full native EPS security context is available, a K_eNB re-keying procedure making use of one of these contexts shall be invoked, otherwise a K_eNB re-keying procedure deriving a new K_eNB<!-- EPO <DP n="16"> --> from the current K_ASME shall be invoked. The precise nature of the trigger conditions is left to implementation.</p>
<p id="p0061" num="0061">NOTE: An example of such a trigger condition is as follows: The number of failed S1 HOs after initial K_eNB establishment is counted, and when this counter reaches the value 5 then the establishment of a new K_eNB is triggered.</p>
<heading id="h0007"><b>7.2.9.2 K_eNB re-keying</b></heading>
<p id="p0062" num="0062">The re-keying procedure is initiated by the MME after a successful AKA run with the UE to activate a partial native EPS security context, or to re-activate a non-current full native EPS security context after handover from GERAN or UTRAN according to subclauses 9.2.2.1 and 10.3.2, or to create a new K_eNB from the current K_ASME.</p>
<p id="p0063" num="0063">In case the procedure is initiated by the MME after a successful AKA run with the UE, the MME derives the new K_eNB using the key derivation function as specified in Annex A.3 using the new K_ASME and the uplink NAS COUNT used in the most recent NAS Security Mode Complete message. The K_eNB is sent to the eNB after a successfully completed NAS SMC in a S1 AP UE CONTEXT MODIFICATION REQUEST message triggering the eNB to perform the re-keying. The eNB runs the key-change-on-the-fly procedure with the UE. During this procedure the eNB shall indicate to the UE that a key change on-the-fly is taking place. The procedure used is based on an intra-cell handover, and hence the same K_eNB derivation steps shall be taken as in a normal handover procedure.</p>
<p id="p0064" num="0064">When the UE receives an indication that the procedure is a key change on-the-fly procedure, the UE shall use the K_ASME from the current EPS NAS security context as the basis for K_eNB derivations.</p>
<p id="p0065" num="0065">NOTE 1: To perform a key change on-the-fly of the entire key hierarchy, the MME has to change the EPS NAS security context before changing the AS security context.</p>
<p id="p0066" num="0066">If the UE has determined that the eKSI has changed, the UE shall derive a temporary K_eNB by applying the key derivation function as specified in Annex A.3, using the uplink NAS COUNT in the most recent NAS Security Mode Complete message and the new K_ASME as input. From this temporary K_eNB the UE shall derive the K_eNB* as normal (see clause A.5). The eNB shall take the K_eNB it received from the MME, which is equal to the temporary K_eNB, as basis for its K_eNB* derivations. From this step onwards, the key derivations continue as in a normal handover.<!-- EPO <DP n="17"> --></p>
<p id="p0067" num="0067">If the AS level re-keying fails, then the MME shall complete another NAS security mode procedure before initiating a new AS level re-keying. This ensures that a fresh K_eNB is used.</p>
<p id="p0068" num="0068">In case the re-keying procedure is initiated by the MME to re-activate a non-current full native EPS security context after handover from GERAN or UTRAN the same procedure as above applies.</p>
<p id="p0069" num="0069">In case the re-keying procedure is meant to create a new K_eNB from the current K_ASME the MME shall first initiate a NAS SMC procedure with the same eKSI and NAS algorithms as in the current EPS NAS security context. The purpose of this NAS SMC procedure is solely to update the parameter 'uplink NAS COUNT used in the latest NAS Security Mode Complete message'. All other parameters in the current EPS NAS security context remain unchanged. The MME computes a new K_eNB using this uplink NAS COUNT, according to Annex A.3, and sends it to the eNB in a S1 AP UE CONTEXT MODIFICATION REQUEST message triggering the eNB to perform the re-keying. The remainder of the procedure is as described above.</p>
<p id="p0070" num="0070">One condition for invoking a re-keying procedure that creates a new K_eNB from the current K_ASME is described in clause 7.2.8.4.3. Invocations of this procedure by other trigger conditions are subject to operator policy.</p>
<p id="p0071" num="0071">For all variants of a K_eNB re-keying procedure, the NH parameter shall be handled according to the following rules:
<ul id="ul0003" list-style="dash" compact="compact">
<li>UE and MME shall use NH derived from old K_ASME before the context modification is complete, i.e. for the UE when it sends the RRC Connection Reconfiguration Complete, and for the MME when it receives the UE CONTEXT MODIFICATION RESPONSE. In particular, the MME shall send an NH derived from old K_ASME in the S1AP HANDOVER RESOURCE ALLOCATION, S10 FORWARD RELOCATION, and S1AP PATH SWITCH REQUEST ACKNOWLEDGE messages before the context modification is complete.</li>
<li>The eNB shall delete any old NH upon completion of the context modification.</li>
<li>The UE and MME shall delete any old NH upon completion of the context modification. After the completion of the context modification, the UE and the MME shall derive any new NH parameters from the new K_eNB and the new K_ASME according to Annex A.4.</li>
</ul><!-- EPO <DP n="18"> --></p>
<p id="p0072" num="0072"><figref idref="f0004">Figure 4</figref> shows, supplementing the above description of aspects of the invention, a basic block circuit diagram of a network entity such as a eNB and/or MME, in which embodiments of the present invention are implemented. Thus, the entity 4 can be any kind of eNB, e.g. a source eNB, SeNB, or a target enB, TeNB, and may also unite SeNB or HeNB properties/functionalities in some scenarios with those of a mobility management entity MME.</p>
<p id="p0073" num="0073">The eNB/MME, denoted by numeral 4, comprises a interface, Tx/Rx, cf. numeral 43, for transmission to / reception from another EPS network entity, e.g. another eNB and/or a UE. The interface is bidirectional connected to a control module or unit such as a processor, e.g. a digital signal processor, DSP, or ASIC (ASIC = application specific integrated circuit), CPU (central processing unit), or the like, denoted by numeral 42. The control module or unit (aka controller) is bidirectional connected to a memory module or unit (aka memory) MEM, denoted by numeral 41. The memory module can be any type of memory to which data can be written and from which data can be read, e.g. a Flash memory, RAM (Random Access Memory), or also EPROM (Electrically Programmable Read Only Memory). The memory module is configured to store at least data necessary for implementation of the invention, e.g. control code, acquired and/or processed data to be used for implementing/realizing at least aspects of the invention.</p>
<p id="p0074" num="0074">Thus, the memory module can be a separate memory module or a partition of a memory module storing also other user/control data handled by the eNB/MME. Other memory modules may be present, too, in the entity. Examples of the invention can be embodied in an apparatus or unit of the eNB/MME, e.g. denoted by numeral 40, comprising at least the modules 42 and 41 above.</p>
<p id="p0075" num="0075">Note that embodiments of the present invention may be implemented in software, hardware, application logic or a combination of software, hardware and application logic. The software, application logic and/or hardware generally resides on a module or unit, or chipset or apparatus associated to a device, i.e. mounted/inserted or mountable/insertable to or configured as a part of such a device, such as a network entity like an MSS or similar functionality.<!-- EPO <DP n="19"> --></p>
<p id="p0076" num="0076">In an example embodiment, the application logic, software or an instruction set is maintained on any one of various conventional computer-readable media. In the context of this document, a "computer-readable medium" may be any media or means that can contain, store, communicate, propagate or transport the instructions for use by or in connection with an instruction execution system, apparatus, or device, such as a computer or smart phone, or user equipment.</p>
<p id="p0077" num="0077">If desired, the different functions discussed herein may be performed in a different order and/or concurrently with each other. Furthermore, if desired, one or more of the above-described functions may be optional or may be combined.</p>
<p id="p0078" num="0078">Although the above description focused on an algorithm aspect, it is to be understood that the algorithm is configurable to corresponding hardware or implemented as software code loaded to a processor.</p>
<p id="p0079" num="0079">Although various aspects of the invention are set out in the independent claims, other aspects of the invention comprise other combinations of features from the described embodiments and/or the dependent claims with the features of the independent claims, and not solely the combinations explicitly set out in the claims.</p>
<p id="p0080" num="0080">It is also noted herein that while the above describes example embodiments of the invention, these descriptions should not be viewed in a limiting sense. Rather, there are several variations and modifications which may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention as defined in the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p0081" num="0081">The present invention proposes computer program claims, methods and apparatuses enabling to improve security in handovers in mobile communication networks, and for example, an apparatus, comprising a memory unit; and a control unit connected to the memory unit, the apparatus being configured to interface at least one access node, wherein the control unit of the apparatus is configured to process one or more higher level<!-- EPO <DP n="20"> --> security keys received from a network entity to derive at least one local level security key within an established security context for a terminal, forward said derived local security key to at least one access node, detect failures in a handover for a terminal being served by a first access node towards a second access node, wherein the failures in the handover concern the interface between the apparatus and said second access node, verify a trigger condition, and, in response to the trigger condition verified, invoke a context modification procedure to re-adjust local level security keys with keys maintained at the terminal within the established security context. According to aspects thereof this leads to advantages of suppression of a key change performed by a terminal, and prevention of a AKA run.</p>
<heading id="h0008"><u>List of some acronyms and abbreviations as used herein above:</u></heading>
<p id="p0082" num="0082">
<dl id="dl0001">
<dt>HO</dt><dd>handover</dd>
<dt>RRM</dt><dd>Radio Resource Management</dd>
<dt>UE</dt><dd>User Equipment</dd>
<dt>HeNB</dt><dd>Host eNodeB</dd>
<dt>SeNB</dt><dd>Source eNodeB</dd>
<dt>TeNB</dt><dd>Target eNodeB</dd>
<dt>EPS</dt><dd>Evolved Packet System</dd>
</dl></p>
<p id="p0083" num="0083">Other acronyms are conformant to those mentioned in 3GPP TR 21.905 or 3GPP TS 33.401.</p>
</description>
<claims id="claims01" lang="en"><!-- EPO <DP n="21"> -->
<claim id="c-en-01-0001" num="0001">
<claim-text>An apparatus (1), comprising
<claim-text>a memory unit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control unit connected to the memory unit,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the apparatus (1) being configured as a functional unit of a network mobility entity to interface at least one access node (2; 3),</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the control unit is configured to
<claim-text>process one or more higher level security keys received from a network entity to derive at least one local level security key within an established security context for a terminal (4),</claim-text>
<claim-text>forward said derived at least one local level security key to the at least one access node (2; 3), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>invoke a context modification procedure to re-adjust the at least one local level security key with at least one local level security key maintained at the terminal (4) within the established security context,</claim-text></claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a re-keying procedure for the at least one access node (2; 3) is performed in which a network access stratum security mode command procedure is initiated, and an updated network access stratum count parameter of a most recent network access stratum security mode command message is obtained, with the updated network access stratum parameter being used to derive a new key for the at least one access node (2; 3) computed based on an existing higher level security key, the new key being provided to the at least one access node (2; 3) for a radio resource control reconfiguration performed between the at least one access node (2; 3) and the terminal (4), and the re-keying procedure being performed without performing an Authentication and Key Agreement procedure.</claim-text><!-- EPO <DP n="22"> --></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0002" num="0002">
<claim-text>The apparatus (1) according to claim 1, wherein<br/>
the at least one local level security key is a next hop, NH, key and a next hop chaining counter, NCC, being used as a key.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0003" num="0003">
<claim-text>The apparatus (1) according to claim 1, wherein
<claim-text>a trigger condition is verified by the apparatus (1), wherein responsive to the trigger condition verified the apparatus (1) invokes the context modification procedure, and wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the trigger condition represents a number of past failed handovers in a handover procedure concerning an interface between the apparatus (1) and said at least one access node (2; 3) representing a target access node (3) to which the terminal (4) is to be handed over.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0004" num="0004">
<claim-text>The apparatus (1) according to claim 3, wherein<br/>
the number of past failed handovers depends on the maximum number of next hop chaining counter, NCC, as at least one of the local level security keys.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0005" num="0005">
<claim-text>The apparatus (1) according to claim 1, wherein<br/>
the context modification procedure invoked is a terminal context modification procedure associated to the terminal (4) to be handed over.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0006" num="0006">
<claim-text>The apparatus according to claim 5, wherein<br/>
the control unit is configured to
<claim-text>compose a terminal context modification request message comprising a latest one of the at least one local level security key, wherein next hop chaining counter, NCC, as at least one of the local level security keys is included in a distinct information element, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forward the distinct information element to the at least one access node (2; 3) representing a source access node (2) from which the terminal (4) is to be handed over.</claim-text><!-- EPO <DP n="23"> --></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0007" num="0007">
<claim-text>The apparatus (1) according to claim 1, wherein<br/>
the context modification procedure invoked is a network access stratum security mode procedure associated to the terminal (4) to be handed over.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0008" num="0008">
<claim-text>The apparatus (1) according to claim 7, wherein<br/>
the control unit is further configured to
<claim-text>initiate a new network access stratum security mode procedure based on an evolved key set identifier, eKSI, and associated algorithms</claim-text>
<claim-text>obtain, as a result thereof, an updated network access stratum parameter for such procedure,</claim-text>
<claim-text>process the obtained updated parameter together with an intermediate base key of an access security management entity, K_ASME, to derive thereform a fresh access node base key, K_eNB, as the at least one of the local level security key, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forward the fresh access node base key to the at least one access node (2; 3).</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0009" num="0009">
<claim-text>A method, comprising
<claim-text>processing one or more higher level security keys received from a network entity to derive at least one local level security key within an established security context for a terminal (4),</claim-text>
<claim-text>forwarding said derived at least one local level security key to the at least one access node (2; 3), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>invoking a context modification procedure to re-adjust the at least one local level security key with at least one local level security key maintained at the terminal (4) within the established security context</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a re-keying procedure for the at least one access node (2; 3) is performed in which a network access stratum security mode command procedure is initiated, and an updated network access stratum count parameter of a most recent network access stratum security mode command message is obtained, with the updated network access stratum parameter being used to derive a new key for the at least one access node (2; 3) computed based on an existing higher<!-- EPO <DP n="24"> --> level security key, the new key being provided to the at least one access node (2; 3) for a radio resource control reconfiguration performed between the at least one access node (2; 3) and the terminal (4), and the re-keying procedure being performed without performing an Authentication and Key Agreement procedure.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0010" num="0010">
<claim-text>The method according to claim 9, wherein<br/>
the at least one local level security key is a next hop, NH, key and a next hop chaining counter, NCC, being used as a key.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0011" num="0011">
<claim-text>The method according to claim 9, wherein the method further comprises
<claim-text>verifying a trigger condition and performing the invoking of the context modification procedure responsive to the trigger condition verified, and wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the trigger condition represents a number of past failed handovers in a handover procedure concerning an interface between another network entity (1) and said at least one access node (2; 3) representing a target access node to which the terminal (4) is to be handed over.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0012" num="0012">
<claim-text>The method according to claim 11, wherein<br/>
the number of past failed handovers depends on a maximum number of a next hop chaining counter, NCC, as at least one of the local level security keys.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0013" num="0013">
<claim-text>The method according to claim 9, wherein<br/>
the context modification procedure invoked is a network access stratum security mode procedure associated to the terminal (4) to be handed over.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0014" num="0014">
<claim-text>The method according to claim 13, wherein<br/>
the method further comprises
<claim-text>initiating a new network access stratum security mode procedure based on an evolved key set identifier, eKSI, and associated algorithms</claim-text>
<claim-text>obtaining, as a result thereof, an updated network access stratum<!-- EPO <DP n="25"> --> parameter for such procedure,</claim-text>
<claim-text>processing the obtained updated parameter together with an intermediate base key of an access security management entity, K_ASME, to derive thereform a fresh access node base key, K_eNB, as the at least one of the local level security key, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forwarding the fresh access node base key to the at least one access node (2; 3).</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-01-0015" num="0015">
<claim-text>A computer program product comprising computer-executable components which, when the program is run on a computer, are configured to perform the method steps according to any of claims 9 to 14.</claim-text></claim>
</claims>
<claims id="claims02" lang="de"><!-- EPO <DP n="26"> -->
<claim id="c-de-01-0001" num="0001">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung (1), die Folgendes umfasst
<claim-text>eine Speichereinheit; und</claim-text>
<claim-text>eine Steuereinheit, die mit der Speichereinheit verbunden ist,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wobei die Vorrichtung (1) als eine Funktionseinheit einer Netzwerkmobilitätsentität ausgelegt ist, um sich an mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) anzubinden,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wobei die Steuereinheit zu Folgendem ausgelegt ist Verarbeiten von einem oder mehreren Sicherheitsschlüsseln höherer Ebene, die von einer Netzwerkentität empfangen werden, um mindestens einen Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene in einem festgelegten Sicherheitskontext für ein Endgerät (4) abzuleiten,</claim-text>
<claim-text>Weiterleiten des abgeleiteten mindestens einen Sicherheitsschlüssels lokaler Ebene zu dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3), und</claim-text>
<claim-text>Aufrufen einer Kontextmodifikationsprozedur, um den mindestens einen Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene mit mindestens einem Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene, der am Endgerät (4) gehalten wird, im festgelegten Sicherheitskontext neu anzupassen,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wobei eine Schlüsselneuerstellungsprozedur für den mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) durchgeführt wird, bei der eine Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusbefehlsprozedur initiiert wird, und ein aktualisierter Netzwerkzugangsschichtzählparameter einer neuesten Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusbefehlsnachricht erhalten wird, wobei der aktualisierte Netzwerkzugangsschichtparameter verwendet wird, um einen neuen Schlüssel für den mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) abzuleiten, der auf Basis eines existierenden Sicherheitsschlüssels höherer Ebene berechnet wird, wobei der<!-- EPO <DP n="27"> --> neue Schlüssel dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) für eine Funkressourcensteuerungsneuauslegung bereitgestellt wird, die zwischen dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) und dem Endgerät (4) durchgeführt wird, und wobei die Schlüsselneuerstellungsprozedur durchgeführt wird, ohne eine Authentifizierungs- und Schlüsselvereinbarungsprozedur durchzuführen.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0002" num="0002">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung (1) nach Anspruch 1, wobei<br/>
der mindestens eine Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene ein Next-Hop(NH)-Schlüssel und ein Next-Hop-Verkettungszähler, NCC, ist, der als ein Schlüssel verwendet wird.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0003" num="0003">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung (1) nach Anspruch 1, wobei
<claim-text>eine Auslösebedingung von der Vorrichtung (1) verifiziert wird, wobei in Reaktion auf die verifizierte Auslösebedingung die Vorrichtung (1) die Kontextmodifikationsprozedur aufruft, und wobei</claim-text>
<claim-text>die Auslösebedingung eine Anzahl von vergangenen fehlgeschlagenen Übergaben bei einer Übergabeprozedur repräsentiert, die eine Schnittstelle zwischen der Vorrichtung (1) und dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) betrifft, der den Zielzugangsknoten (3) repräsentiert, an den das Endgerät (4) zu übergeben ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0004" num="0004">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung (1) nach Anspruch 3, wobei<br/>
die Anzahl von vergangenen fehlgeschlagenen Übergaben von der maximalen Anzahl eines Next-Hop-Verkettungszählers, NCC, als mindestens einem der Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene abhängig ist.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0005" num="0005">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung (1) nach Anspruch 1, wobei<br/>
<!-- EPO <DP n="28"> -->die aufgerufene Kontextmodifikationsprozedur eine Endgerätekontextmodifikationsprozedur ist, die mit dem Endgerät (4), das zu übergeben ist, verknüpft ist.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0006" num="0006">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 5, wobei
<claim-text>die Steuereinheit zu Folgendem ausgelegt ist</claim-text>
<claim-text>Verfassen einer Endgerätekontextmodifikationsanforderungsnachricht, die einen letzten des mindestens einen Sicherheitsschlüssels lokaler Ebene umfasst, wobei der Next-Hop-Verkettungszähler, NCC, als mindestens einer des Sicherheitsschlüssels lokaler Ebene in einem eindeutigen Informationselement beinhaltet ist, und</claim-text>
<claim-text>Weiterleiten des eindeutigen Informationselements zu dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3), der einen Quellzugangsknoten (2) repräsentiert, von dem das Endgerät (4) zu übergeben ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0007" num="0007">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung (1) nach Anspruch 1, wobei<br/>
die aufgerufene Kontextmodifikationsprozedur eine Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusprozedur ist, die mit dem Endgerät (4), das zu übergeben ist, verknüpft ist.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0008" num="0008">
<claim-text>Vorrichtung (1) nach Anspruch 7, wobei
<claim-text>die Steuereinheit ferner zu Folgendem ausgelegt ist Initiieren einer neuen Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusprozedur auf Basis einer entwickelten Schlüsselsatzkennung, eKSI, und von zugehörigen Algorithmen</claim-text>
<claim-text>Erhalten eines aktualisierten Netzwerkzugangsschichtparameters für eine derartige Prozedur als ein Ergebnis davon,</claim-text>
<claim-text>Verarbeiten des erhaltenen aktualisierten Parameters zusammen mit einem Zwischenbasisschlüssel einer<!-- EPO <DP n="29"> --> Zugangssicherheitsverwaltungsentität, K_ASME, um daraus einen frischen Zugangsknotenbasisschlüssel, K_eNB, als den mindestens einen des Sicherheitsschlüssels lokaler Ebene abzuleiten, und</claim-text>
<claim-text>Weiterleiten des frischen Zugangsknotenbasisschlüssels zu dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3).</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0009" num="0009">
<claim-text>Verfahren, das Folgendes umfasst
<claim-text>Verarbeiten von einem oder mehreren Sicherheitsschlüsseln höherer Ebene, die von einer Netzwerkentität empfangen werden, um mindestens einen Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene in einem festgelegten Sicherheitskontext für ein Endgerät (4) abzuleiten,</claim-text>
<claim-text>Weiterleiten des abgeleiteten mindestens einen Sicherheitsschlüssels lokaler Ebene zu dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3), und</claim-text>
<claim-text>Aufrufen einer Kontextmodifikationsprozedur, um den mindestens einen Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene mit mindestens einem Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene, der am Endgerät (4) gehalten wird, im festgelegten Sicherheitskontext neu anzupassen</claim-text>
<claim-text>wobei eine Schlüsselneuerstellungsprozedur für den mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) durchgeführt wird, bei der eine Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusbefehlsprozedur initiiert wird, und ein aktualisierter Netzwerkzugangsschichtzählparameter einer neuesten Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusbefehlsnachricht erhalten wird, wobei der aktualisierte Netzwerkzugangsschichtparameter verwendet wird, um einen neuen Schlüssel für den mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) abzuleiten, der auf Basis eines existierenden Sicherheitsschlüssels höherer Ebene berechnet wird, wobei der neue Schlüssel dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) für eine Funkressourcensteuerungsneuauslegung bereitgestellt wird, die zwischen dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) und dem<!-- EPO <DP n="30"> --> Endgerät (4) durchgeführt wird, und wobei die Schlüsselneuerstellungsprozedur durchgeführt wird, ohne eine Authentifizierungs- und Schlüsselvereinbarungsprozedur durchzuführen.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0010" num="0010">
<claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 9, wobei<br/>
der mindestens eine Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene ein Next-Hop(NH)-Schlüssel und ein Next-Hop-Verkettungszähler, NCC, ist, der als ein Schlüssel verwendet wird.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0011" num="0011">
<claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 9, wobei das Verfahren ferner Folgendes umfasst
<claim-text>Verifizieren einer Auslösebedingung und Durchführen des Aufrufens der Kontextmodifikationsprozedur in Reaktion auf die verifizierte Auslösebedingung, und wobei</claim-text>
<claim-text>die Auslösebedingung eine Anzahl von vergangenen fehlgeschlagenen Übergaben bei einer Übergabeprozedur repräsentiert, die eine Schnittstelle zwischen einer weiteren Netzwerkentität (1) und dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3) betrifft, der den Zielzugangsknoten repräsentiert, an den das Endgerät (4) zu übergeben ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0012" num="0012">
<claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 11, wobei<br/>
die Anzahl von vergangenen fehlgeschlagenen Übergaben von einer maximalen Anzahl eines Next-Hop-Verkettungszählers, NCC, als mindestens einem der Sicherheitsschlüssel lokaler Ebene abhängig ist.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0013" num="0013">
<claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 9, wobei<br/>
die aufgerufene Kontextmodifikationsprozedur eine Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusprozedur ist, die mit dem Endgerät (4), das zu übergeben ist, verknüpft ist.<!-- EPO <DP n="31"> --></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0014" num="0014">
<claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 13, wobei
<claim-text>das Verfahren ferner Folgendes umfasst</claim-text>
<claim-text>Initiieren einer neuen Netzwerkzugangsschichtsicherheitsmodusprozedur auf Basis einer entwickelten Schlüsselsatzkennung, eKSI, und von zugehörigen Algorithmen</claim-text>
<claim-text>Erhalten eines aktualisierten Netzwerkzugangsschichtparameters für eine derartige Prozedur als ein Ergebnis davon,</claim-text>
<claim-text>Verarbeiten des erhaltenen aktualisierten Parameters zusammen mit einem Zwischenbasisschlüssel einer Zugangssicherheitsverwaltungsentität, K_ASME, um daraus einen frischen Zugangsknotenbasisschlüssel, K_eNB, als den mindestens einen des Sicherheitsschlüssels lokaler Ebene abzuleiten, und</claim-text>
<claim-text>Weiterleiten des frischen Zugangsknotenbasisschlüssels zu dem mindestens einen Zugangsknoten (2; 3).</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-de-01-0015" num="0015">
<claim-text>Computerprogrammprodukt, das computerausführbare Komponenten umfasst, die, wenn das Programm auf einem Computer läuft, dazu ausgelegt sind, die Verfahrensschritte nach einem der Ansprüche 9 bis 14 durchzuführen.</claim-text></claim>
</claims>
<claims id="claims03" lang="fr"><!-- EPO <DP n="32"> -->
<claim id="c-fr-01-0001" num="0001">
<claim-text>Appareil (1), comprenant
<claim-text>une unité de mémoire ; et</claim-text>
<claim-text>une unité de commande connectée à l'unité de mémoire, l'appareil (1) étant configuré comme une unité fonctionnelle d'une entité de mobilité de réseau pour interfacer au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3),</claim-text>
<claim-text>dans lequel l'unité de commande est configurée pour
<claim-text>traiter une ou plusieurs clés de sécurité de niveau supérieur reçues à partir d'une entité de réseau pour dériver au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local dans un contexte de sécurité établi pour un terminal (4),</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmettre ladite au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local dérivée à l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3), et</claim-text>
<claim-text>invoquer une procédure de modification de contexte pour régler à nouveau l'au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local avec au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local maintenue au niveau dudit terminal (4) dans le contexte de sécurité établi,</claim-text></claim-text>
<claim-text>dans lequel, au cours d'une procédure d'actualisation de clé réalisée pour l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3), une procédure d'instruction de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau est initiée, et un paramètre de comptage de strate d'accès au réseau mis à jour du message d'instruction de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau le plus récent est obtenu, le paramètre de strate d'accès au réseau mis à jour étant utilisé pour dériver une nouvelle clé pour l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) calculée sur la base d'une clé de sécurité de niveau supérieur existante, la nouvelle clé étant fournie à l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) pour une reconfiguration de contrôle de ressource radio réalisée entre l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) et le terminal (4), et la procédure<!-- EPO <DP n="33"> --> d'actualisation de clé étant réalisée sans réaliser de procédure d'authentification et d'accord de clé.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0002" num="0002">
<claim-text>Appareil (1) selon la revendication 1, dans lequel l'au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local est une clé de saut suivant, NH, et un compteur de chaînage de saut suivant, NCC, est utilisé comme clé.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0003" num="0003">
<claim-text>Appareil (1) selon la revendication 1, dans lequel
<claim-text>une condition de déclenchement est vérifiée par l'appareil (1), dans lequel, en réponse à la condition de déclenchement vérifiée, l'appareil (1) invoque la procédure de modification de contexte, et dans lequel</claim-text>
<claim-text>la condition de déclenchement représente un nombre de transferts intercellulaires antérieurs qui ont échoué dans une procédure de transfert intercellulaire concernant une interface entre l'appareil (1) et ledit au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) représentant un noeud d'accès cible (3) vers lequel le terminal (4) doit être soumis à un transfert intercellulaire.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0004" num="0004">
<claim-text>Appareil (1) selon la revendication 3, dans lequel<br/>
le nombre de transferts intercellulaires antérieurs qui ont échoué dépend du nombre maximal de compteurs de chaînage de saut suivant, NCC, comme au moins une des clés de sécurité de niveau local.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0005" num="0005">
<claim-text>Appareil (1) selon la revendication 1, dans lequel<br/>
la procédure de modification de contexte invoquée est une procédure de modification de contexte de terminal associée au terminal (4) devant être soumis à un transfert intercellulaire.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0006" num="0006">
<claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 5, dans lequel<br/>
l'unité de commande est configurée pour<!-- EPO <DP n="34"> -->
<claim-text>composer un message de demande de modification de contexte de terminal comprenant une dernière clé de la ou des clés de sécurité de niveau local, dans lequel le compteur de chaînage de saut suivant, NCC, comme au moins une des clés de sécurité de niveau local, est inclus dans un élément d'information distinct, et</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmettre l'élément d'information distinct à l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) représentant un noeud d'accès source (2) à partir duquel le terminal (4) doit être soumis à un transfert intercellulaire.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0007" num="0007">
<claim-text>Appareil (1) selon la revendication 1, dans lequel la procédure de modification de contexte invoquée est une procédure de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau associée au terminal (4) devant être soumis à un transfert intercellulaire.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0008" num="0008">
<claim-text>Appareil (1) selon la revendication 7, dans lequel<br/>
l'unité de commande est en outre configurée pour
<claim-text>initier une nouvelle procédure de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau sur la base d'un identifiant d'ensemble de clés évolué, eKSI, et d'algorithmes associés,</claim-text>
<claim-text>obtenir, comme résultat de ceci, un paramètre de strate d'accès au réseau mis à jour pour cette procédure,</claim-text>
<claim-text>traiter le paramètre mis à jour obtenu en même temps qu'une clé de base intermédiaire d'une entité de gestion de sécurité d'accès, K_ASME, pour en dériver une clé de base de noeud d'accès rafraîchie, K_eNB, comme l'au moins une clé de la ou des clés de sécurité de niveau local, et</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmettre la clé de base de noeud d'accès rafraîchie à l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3).</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0009" num="0009">
<claim-text>Procédé, comprenant<!-- EPO <DP n="35"> -->
<claim-text>le traitement d'une ou plusieurs clés de sécurité de niveau supérieur reçue à partir d'une entité de réseau pour dériver au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local dans un contexte de sécurité établi pour un terminal (4),</claim-text>
<claim-text>la transmission de ladite au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local dérivée à l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3), et</claim-text>
<claim-text>l'invocation d'une procédure de modification de contexte pour régler à nouveau l'au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local avec au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local maintenue au niveau dudit terminal (4) dans le contexte de sécurité établi</claim-text>
<claim-text>dans lequel, au cours d'une procédure d'actualisation de clé réalisée pour l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3), une procédure d'instruction de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau est initiée, et un paramètre de comptage de strate d'accès au réseau mis à jour du message d'instruction de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau le plus récent est obtenu, le paramètre de strate d'accès au réseau mis à jour étant utilisé pour dériver une nouvelle clé pour l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) calculée sur la base d'une clé de sécurité de niveau supérieur existante, la nouvelle clé étant fournie à l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) pour une reconfiguration de contrôle de ressource radio réalisée entre l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) et le terminal (4), et la procédure d'actualisation de clé étant réalisée sans réaliser de procédure d'authentification et d'accord de clé.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0010" num="0010">
<claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 9, dans lequel<br/>
l'au moins une clé de sécurité de niveau local est une clé de saut suivant, NH, et un compteur de chaînage de saut suivant, NCC, est utilisé comme clé.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0011" num="0011">
<claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 9, dans lequel le procédé comprend en outre<!-- EPO <DP n="36"> -->
<claim-text>la vérification d'une condition de déclenchement et la réalisation de l'invocation de la procédure de modification de contexte en réponse à la condition de déclenchement vérifiée, et dans lequel</claim-text>
<claim-text>la condition de déclenchement représente un nombre de transferts intercellulaires antérieurs qui ont échoué dans une procédure de transfert intercellulaire concernant une interface entre une autre entité de réseau (1) et ledit au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3) représentant un noeud d'accès cible vers lequel le terminal (4) doit être soumis à un transfert intercellulaire.</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0012" num="0012">
<claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 11, dans lequel<br/>
le nombre de transferts intercellulaires antérieurs qui ont échoué dépend du nombre maximal de compteurs de chaînage de saut suivant, NCC, comme au moins une des clés de sécurité de niveau local.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0013" num="0013">
<claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 9, dans lequel<br/>
la procédure de modification de contexte invoquée est une procédure de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau associée au terminal (4) devant être soumis à un transfert intercellulaire.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0014" num="0014">
<claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 13, dans lequel<br/>
le procédé comprend en outre
<claim-text>l'initiation d'une nouvelle procédure de mode de sécurité de strate d'accès au réseau sur la base d'un identifiant d'ensemble de clés évolué, eKSI, et d'algorithmes associés</claim-text>
<claim-text>l'obtention, comme résultat de ceci, d'un paramètre de strate d'accès au réseau mis à jour pour cette procédure,</claim-text>
<claim-text>le traitement du paramètre mis à jour obtenu en même temps qu'une clé de base intermédiaire d'une entité de gestion de sécurité d'accès, K_ASME, pour en dériver une clé de base de<!-- EPO <DP n="37"> --> noeud d'accès rafraîchie, K_eNB, comme l'au moins une clé de la ou des clés de sécurité de niveau local, et</claim-text>
<claim-text>la transmission de la clé de base de noeud d'accès rafraîchie à l'au moins un noeud d'accès (2 ; 3).</claim-text></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-fr-01-0015" num="0015">
<claim-text>Produit de programme informatique comprenant des composants exécutables par ordinateur qui, lorsque le programme est exécuté sur un ordinateur, sont configurés pour réaliser les étapes du procédé selon l'une des revendications 9 à 14.</claim-text></claim>
</claims>
<drawings id="draw" lang="en"><!-- EPO <DP n="38"> -->
<figure id="f0001" num="1"><img id="if0001" file="imgf0001.tif" wi="148" he="112" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/></figure><!-- EPO <DP n="39"> -->
<figure id="f0002" num="2"><img id="if0002" file="imgf0002.tif" wi="150" he="219" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/></figure><!-- EPO <DP n="40"> -->
<figure id="f0003" num="3"><img id="if0003" file="imgf0003.tif" wi="150" he="217" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/></figure><!-- EPO <DP n="41"> -->
<figure id="f0004" num="4"><img id="if0004" file="imgf0004.tif" wi="142" he="94" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/></figure>
</drawings>
<ep-reference-list id="ref-list">
<heading id="ref-h0001"><b>REFERENCES CITED IN THE DESCRIPTION</b></heading>
<p id="ref-p0001" num=""><i>This list of references cited by the applicant is for the reader's convenience only. It does not form part of the European patent document. Even though great care has been taken in compiling the references, errors or omissions cannot be excluded and the EPO disclaims all liability in this regard.</i></p>
<heading id="ref-h0002"><b>Patent documents cited in the description</b></heading>
<p id="ref-p0002" num="">
<ul id="ref-ul0001" list-style="bullet">
<li><patcit id="ref-pcit0001" dnum="EP2197147A1"><document-id><country>EP</country><doc-number>2197147</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></patcit><crossref idref="pcit0001">[0025]</crossref></li>
<li><patcit id="ref-pcit0002" dnum="GB2472580A"><document-id><country>GB</country><doc-number>2472580</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit><crossref idref="pcit0002">[0025]</crossref></li>
</ul></p>
<heading id="ref-h0003"><b>Non-patent literature cited in the description</b></heading>
<p id="ref-p0003" num="">
<ul id="ref-ul0002" list-style="bullet">
<li><nplcit id="ref-ncit0001" npl-type="s"><article><atl/><serial><sertitle>3GPP Standard; 3GPP TS 33.401</sertitle><pubdate><sdate>20121024</sdate><edate/></pubdate><vid>SA WG3</vid><ino>V12.5.1</ino></serial></article></nplcit><crossref idref="ncit0001">[0025]</crossref></li>
</ul></p>
</ep-reference-list>
</ep-patent-document>
